Guide to the Olga Rudge Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Olga Rudge Papers
1887-1989
YCAL MSS 54
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
87.5
(163 boxes)
The Olga Rudge Papers document many aspects of Rudge's personal life and professional activities. There are 32 boxes of letters between Ezra Pound and Rudge. Other major correspondents include Mary de Rachewiltz, James Laughlin, George Antheil, Renata Borgatti, conte Guido Chigi Saracini, Cyril Connolly, T. S. Eliot, Egerton Grey, Desmond O'Grady, D. D. Paige, Ildebrando Pizzetti, Dorothy Pound, and Adrian Stokes. The papers also contain daily notebooks kept by Rudge from 1966 on; a variety of personal and financial papers; printed material collected by Rudge; and documentation of her musical career, including autograph scores by George Antheil, Tibor Serly, and Julia Perry.
Rudge, Olga, 1895-1996
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1990 from Olga Rudge and the Ezra Pound Foundation.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 163: This box contains material that was formerly restricted until 2016. Legally privileged documents and legal documents that by their terms were governed by confidentiality clauses have been redacted from files P: Negotiations with Yale and Q: Closing documents.
Associated Materials
Additional Ezra Pound material, including correspondence (mostly post-1962), manuscripts, notes and a small quantity of personal papers was acquired in 1990 from the same sources, and these papers have been processed as the Ezra Pound Addition (YCAL MSS 53).
OLGA RUDGE (1895-)
Olga Rudge was born in Youngstown, Ohio on April 13, 1895, the daughter of J. Edgar Rudge, a real estate investor, and Julia O'Connell Rudge, a singer. Around 1905, Julia Rudge moved to Europe with her three children, first to London and then to Paris, in pursuit of her singing career. Olga was educated at St. Anthony's Convent in Sherborne, England and began her musical training early, studying in Paris with the violinist Carambât.
At the outbreak of World War I both of her brothers, Arthur and Teddy, joined the R.A.F.: Arthur Rudge was killed in action in France in 1916. Olga's scrapbooks from the war are filled with notices of her playing at many war benefits and "war entertainments," some sponsored by Isodore de Lara. She also played at the Studio Meeting Society of Mrs. Katherine Dalliba-John, a patroness of Ildebrando Pizzetti who became a supporter of Rudge as well. Late in 1918, Rudge played modern Italian music with Pizzetti in a series of concerts in Italy.
During the war, she was often accompanied by the pianist Percy Kahn; but she began to appear increasingly with Renata Borgatti. Their concert at the Aeolian Hall in November 1920 was reviewed by Ezra Pound in the New Age: he praised the "delicate firmness of her fiddling" but objected to Borgatti's "piano whack."
Rudge continued to pursue her interest in modern Italian music, playing with Pizzetti and at the Sala Bach in Rome with Ernesto Consolo in 1921 and joining Renata Borgatti for a concert of Italian music at the Salle Pleyel in 1922.
Rudge met Ezra Pound in Paris in the summer of 1923. In an article in Il Mare ten years later Pound recalled "her delicate and unemphatic reserve" during their meeting at Natalie Barney's salon. Pound himself was highly interested in music at this time, attempting to compose an opera and promoting the work of American composer George Antheil. Pound and the young violinist soon began a professional collaboration and a personal relationship that was to endure for forty-nine years.
In December of that year Rudge and Antheil played at the Salle du Conservatoire. The program included pieces by Pound, Antheil, Mozart, and Bach. On July 7, 1924 Rudge and Antheil performed "Musique Americaine" at the Salle Pleyel, including two pieces by Pound and the Deuxième Sonate by Antheil, which he dedicated to Rudge.
During 1924, the Pounds were relocating from Paris to Rapallo, and Rudge visited Pound several times in Italy during the summer and fall. By early 1925 the optimistic Antheil was pressing Olga to join him on a musical tour in the United States, but she was unable to accept his invitations due to her pregnancy. She entered the Sanatoria della Cittá Bressanone in June 1925, where Mary Rudge was born on July 9. Pound joined her there at the end of the month, and the child was boarded with a family in the village of Gais.
Rudge resumed her musical career. She played in the debut of Pound's opera, Paroles de Villon, at the Salle Pleyel in June 1926; rejoined Antheil for concerts in Budapest and Rome in 1927; and performed an all-Mozart program with Ernesto Consolo in Florence. With Daniel Amphitheatrow, Rudge played for Mussolini and received an audience with him. During the late 1920s, Rudge traveled constantly between Paris and various Italian cities, occasionally visiting friends and patrons in England as well. In the fall of 1928 she purchased a small house in Venice, 252 Calle Querini, with her father's assistance and began bringing Mary Rudge there for occasional visits, which often included Pound. Beginning in the summer of 1929 she also rented a small house in Sant'Ambrogio, above Rapallo; her yearly stays there gave her further opportunities to see Pound.
During the 1930s Rudge's concert career slackened, in part because the Depression had affected so many of the patrons who had previously sponsored musical performers. In 1933 she joined the Accademia Musicale Chigiana in Siena as its secretary-receptionist, and worked there for part of every year until World War II. Between 1933 and 1939 she also played a prominent part in the Concerti Tigulliani, an annual series of concerts organized and promoted by Pound, along with musicians such as Gerhart Münch and Tibor Serly, and other guest artists.
Rudge and Pound were involved in promoting the music of Antonio Vivaldi. The Concerti Tigulliani for 1936 were devoted to "Vivaldi study" and performances of relatively unknown pieces. Rudge journeyed to Turin to study unedited Vivaldi manuscripts, and Pound obtained microfilm of others from Dresden. Rudge and Pound were both interested in microfilm as an aid in the study of early music manuscripts and tried to promote its use. She attempted to organize a Vivaldi Society with David Nixon in Venice. This failed, but with S. A. Luciani and Antonio Bruers, Rudge founded the Centro di Studi Vivaldiani within the Accademia Chigiana in 1938. The Settimana Vivaldiana was held in Siena in the following year. Organized by Rudge and Luciani and featuring Alfredo Casella, the festival showcased many neglected concerti and the opera L'Olympiade. Rudge's thematic catalogue of the Turin manuscripts was published by the Accademia as part of its Vivaldi homage.
Rudge gradually stopped traveling outside of Italy as the political situation in Europe worsened; her last trip to England took place in the winter of 1935, during the Italian invasion of Ethiopia. She supported Pound in his radio broadcasts and sometimes suggested topics based on newspaper articles or other information. During 1941 she apparently considered accompanying Pound to America, but abandoned this idea when Pound decided not to go.
With the onset of World War II Rudge no longer worked at the Chigiana. Her house in Venice was sequestered after America's entry into the war, and she spent most of her time in San Ambrogio. For the first years of the war she was sometimes accompanied by her daughter Mary, who had been attending a convent school in Florence. Pound continued his series of talks on Italian radio. When the Pounds were ordered out of their seafront apartment in Rapallo late in 1943 as enemy aliens, they moved in with Rudge for the duration of the war, while Mary returned to her foster parents in Gais. The war brought hardship to all of them. Food was scarce, and in the last months of the war the household's only income was the fees Rudge received for giving language lessons.
On May 3, 1945, Pound was arrested by partisans and brought to American army headquarters in Genoa. Rudge accompanied him there, and was released after questioning. Several months passed before she was permitted to correspond with Pound, although she and Mary visited him at least once while he was in detention in Pisa.
At the end of the war, Rudge resumed her work at the Accademia Chigiana, and her house in Venice was restored to her. During Pound's 12-year confinement in St. Elizabeths, she approached his friends and acquaintances with ideas that she hoped might lead to his release. She circulated a petition in Rapallo testifying that Pound had never been a member of the Fascist Party, and suggested to Eliot that Pound might be allowed to retire to a monastery in America. She also dealt with the students and disciples whom Pound sent to her in search of information in the "archives" of his papers at Sant'Ambrogio. She visited Pound in America in 1952 and 1955; after the second visit their correspondence was infrequent for several years.
On Pound's release from the asylum in 1958, he and Dorothy returned to Italy and moved in with his daughter Mary, who had married Boris de Rachewiltz and established residence at Brunnenberg castle in Tirolo. Pound's health deteriorated, and in 1962 he joined Olga Rudge permanently after almost a year in a clinic at Martinsbrunn. For the next ten years Rudge cared for Pound, arranging his schedule and dealing with the increasing numbers of scholars and admirers who wanted contact with him. In 1965 they journeyed to London for the funeral of T. S. Eliot; on their last extended trip, they came to the United States in 1969. Pound died on November 1, 1972, and Rudge took charge of the funeral arrangements in Venice.
Over the next decade Rudge continued to have contact with Pound scholars; she helped organize several exhibits and tributes to Pound and pursued several possible plans for memorials in Idaho and Venice.
Scope and Contents
The Olga Rudge Papers document the life and activities of musician Olga Rudge and her fifty-year relationship with the poet Ezra Pound. The papers span the dates 1887-1989, but the bulk of the material covers the years 1923-80.
The papers are arranged in eleven series. Series I, Rudge-Pound Correspondence, is housed in Boxes 1-32 and consists of the personal correspondence of Olga Rudge and Ezra Pound from 1923 to 1969. This is followed by Series II, General Correspondence (Boxes 33-92), which contains the personal and professional correspondence of Rudge herself. Series III, Notebooks, fills Boxes 93-102 and includes a series of daily I Ching readings and Rudge's comments on them, as well as notes by Rudge on various subjects, often relating to Ezra Pound. Series IV, Personal Papers, is located in Boxes 102-24. Arranged alphabetically by type of material, the series holds Rudge's writings; biographical information, notes and inventories; and a variety of personal memorabilia.
Boxes 119-26 contain Series V, Financial Papers, which include bank statements, bills and receipts, and rental, tax, and utility information. Series VI, Printed Material, is housed in Boxes 127-34 and is arranged alphabetically by subject and type of material. Newspaper Clippings, Series VII (Boxes 135-41) contains clippings and articles on various topics collected by Rudge. Series VIII, Music, is located in Boxes 142-47 and consists of documentation of Rudge's musical career, including scores, publicity, and reviews. Series IX, Photographs (Boxes 148-54) holds photographs of Rudge, Pound, their families and friends, and other subjects. Family Papers are housed in Series X, Boxes 155-56, and include correspondence, personal papers, and photographs relating to the Rudge family, particularly Julia O'Connell Rudge and Arthur Rudge. Series XI, Box 163, contains papers of the Ezra Pound Foundation and has been restricted until 2016. Oversize material is located at the end of the collection, in Boxes 157-164.
Series I, Rudge-Pound Correspondence, occupies Boxes 1-32. Filling over fifteen feet of shelving and spanning almost a half-century, this extensive correspondence provides much information on the personal relationship and professional activities of Rudge and Pound. The correspondence is arranged chronologically, with Pound's and Rudge's letters interfiled. While Rudge habitually dated her letters, Pound was often more careless in this matter. Where no date appears on the letter, conjectural dates have been assigned, on the basis of postmarks (not always reliable in the case of the Rapallo post office), subject matter, and stationery. Letters that cannot be dated more closely than by year are filed at the end of each year; completely undated letters are located at the end of the correspondence.
One of the most remarkable features of Pound's letters to Rudge are the frequent enclosures. Beginning in the 1920s, it was Pound's habit to send on letters and stray pages of letters from his desk as a way of keeping her informed about his daily activities. He also sent, on occasion, manuscripts of his current work, including Cantos and parts of Cantos, for her to read and comment on. The originals of these enclosures have been filed with the Ezra Pound Addition (YCAL MSS 53) and marked with the date of the original Pound letter in which they appeared. They have been replaced in the Olga Rudge Papers by photocopies.
The correspondence begins in Paris in the summer of 1923, with brief notes arranging meetings between the two and with George Antheil. A letter of November 5, for example, tells Rudge "Come here Tuesday at 3:30" and goes on to instruct her "dont buy a ticket for me unless it is something bloody remarkable--remember I wuz a critik for 3 years= + have had enough concerts to last me for life..." The letters for most of 1924 are concerned with the Pounds' move to Italy, arrangements to meet with Rudge in various cities, such as in Genoa in November 1924, and plans for concerts.
As Rudge's pregnancy proceeded in the winter and spring of 1925, their letters became preoccupied with Rudge's medical plans, travel to Bressanone, and the problems of Italian law, as well as Rudge's need to find suitable reasons for declining to join Antheil on a concert tour. Pound's letters also contain anecdotes about the literary scene and news of his own work. A letter of 22 June, for example, contains his opinions of Italian books, the fact that "Mr Hemingway has bust his hand in a proize fite," and Pound's resolve "to assissinate all my contemporaries ... have begun by sending them defamatory letters ..." The summer's letters are devoted to the news of Mary Rudge's birth and Rudge's health; folder 38 contains several letters of congratulation from Pound on varying stationery and in disguised handwriting, although he complained in one that "he can not disguise his handschrift."
Throughout the 1920s, the correspondence is filled with personal news, Pound's literary opinions, enclosed letters from friends, and complex travel arrangements for both. Pound reveals his skill as a publicist in his frequent advice to Rudge on her musical career, the importance of patrons and press notes, and her relations with the mercurial Antheil. Eager to "boom" her 1927 concerts, Pound scolded her lack of attention to press coverage in a January 31 letter: "He is naturally pleased to hear she played the fiddle, but in the early stages of a CAREER the utility of performance is, to say the least, enhanced by allowing the fact to LEAK OUT. DAMN THE EXPENTZ." A calmer letter dated February 21 notes, "All right, she play for Muss," and in the same month Pound praises Marinetti as an "excellent press agent." He frequently comments on his reading. On the 30th of October, he writes: "Have at last seen Hem's great popular novel, very poor with bright spots now-n-again."
During the late 1920s, Pound sent many brief letters describing daily events in Rapallo, particularly mentioning time spent playing tennis or talking with Yeats, as well as reporting on his literary activities and the progress of Exile, while Rudge's letters describe concerts, travel to Capri, France, and England, and her feelings for Pound. The letters of both also contain reports on the health of their daughter Mary and their impressions of her life in Gais. After Rudge's purchase of a house in Venice, many of Pound's letters are occupied with plans for remodeling.
The letters from December of 1928 to January 1930 are perhaps the most open statements about the nature of the Pound-Rudge relationship and each person's perception of it. Apparently in response to a letter from Rudge, Pound wrote a series of letters, beginning with December 9, 1928, explaining his views of their relationship and his theories of personal relations in general, which include the statements "My idea of hell is being expected to do something," and "I have never believed that the affairs of any two people concern a third." The discussion was carried on until Rudge's and Pound's reunion in April of 1929, and renewed in late 1929 and early 1930.
During the 1930s Rudge's life assumed a more regular pattern, with yearly stays in Sant'Ambrogio and time in Venice. Pound's life changed as well, as his parents moved to Rapallo and he became increasingly interested in ecomomics. His December 26, 1929 letters informed Rudge that he had told his father about Mary: "Took him sometime to digest the statement." Increasingly, the Depression became a factor as well. What Rudge referred to in a November 1930 letter as "the American crash" affected patrons like Katherine Dalliba-John, Arturo Brown, and her own father, leaving them unable to finance performances or travel. The letters of the early 1930s contain fewer comments on literature, and scattered asides on the political and financial situations of the United States and Italy.
However, Pound's letters continue to record daily events, including the August 1933 arrival of a postcard from James Laughlin, a "young Hawvud man wants to come to discuss assassinatin all his american elders." From 1933, the letters outline their plans for the Concerti Tigulliani and comment on the performers and concerts, detail Rudge's experiences as "secretary-receptionist" of the Accademia Musicale Chigiana in Siena, and describe the increasing number of Pound's "projects." Vivaldi and microphotography are also important subjects, particularly during Rudge's researches in Turin in 1936.
Political and economic concerns come to the forefront of the correspondence during late 1935 and early 1936. Rudge embarked on her last visit to England shortly after Mussolini invaded Ethiopia, and her letters are filled with reports of the British "attitude," comments on Eden, discussion of the death of King George, and information on Social Credit and the New English Weekly, in answer to Pound's many questions. His lengthy replies describe the many articles and letters he is writing or planning, his disgust with the European condemnation of Mussolini, Social Credit and the need to propagandize for it in France, and their Vivaldi projects.
Pound's letters from London in the fall of 1938 are filled mainly with personal news and descriptions of the London scene; his letters from his trip to America in 1939 are more informative, listing political figures met and opinions exchanged.
Pound noted the outbreak of war on September 1, 1939 with a subdued letter: "Mebbe still some chance of England or Italy keepin out of the shindy...a chance for localizin' the show." Isolated from many of their correspondents and cautious about the Italian censors, both Pound and Rudge wrote mostly brief and mundane letters throughout 1940 and 1941, sometimes in Italian to avoid suspicion, although Pound complained in July 1940 that he "can't say censorship tends all expressione lirica del movimenti del cuore." Letters from the summer of 1940 comment on American political trends, Odon Por, the need of new education for a new era, and his articles for Italian newspapers and the Japan Times. Notes from late 1940 concern his plans to broadcast on Rome Radio.
Finally, on January 21, 1941, Pound was able to write from Rome: "finito la trasmissisone." The following day he reported recording two more talks. His letters from Rome are laconic and often concerned with broadcasting technicalities, requests for quotations or newspaper clippings, and brief lists of persons he has met. During the spring and summer of 1941 the letters often begin with comments on their horoscopes. There are also letters and telegrams concerning Pound's abandoned plans to reserve seats for his family on a Flying Clipper.
After America's entry into the war, Pound and Rudge corresponded mainly during Pound's absences from Rapallo to record radio broadcasts. These letters can be found in Box 23, folders 603-29 and Box 24, folders 630-38. They describe Pound's activities in Rome, technical information about the recording sessions, food, personal news of Rudge and their daughter (now with Rudge in Sant'Ambrogio), and articles in the Italian press. After the fall of Rome, Pound's increasingly infrequent letters arrived from Saló or Milan.
The only correspondence for the year 1945 is a short note dated "24 Giovedi / Maggio," stating "Talk is that I may go to Rome oggi." Rudge has identified this as a letter left for her by Pound on his way to the Pisan detention camp. The next item, an envelope of newspaper clippings from Washington, D. C., is postmarked Dec 24 1945.
The Rudge-Pound correspondence from his years in St. Elizabeths fills Boxes 23-30. The early St. Elizabeths letters contain copies of Confucian odes for Rudge, advice about their daughter Mary and new son-in-law Boris de Rachewiltz, denunciations of American life and politics, descriptions of his visitors, and requests for information. Pound frequently sent Rudge newspaper clippings, often of "animal interest" stories, odd events, or Westbrook Pegler columns. Rudge's letters contain descriptions of her life in Italy, family news, her passport problems, demands for information about Pound's condition, and suggestions for obtaining his release. Pound discouraged her attempts to visit him, saying in an October 1946 letter: "SHE damn well not set foot in this country...It is no place for her. No--when a man is down a well-hole you dont help by jumpin on top of him...NOTHING- to live on for anyone with less than $5000 a year. & hatred for any activity save pillage."
As the years went by, the correspondence often concerns Pound's students and disciples and his projects for them, some requiring Rudge's cooperation. Rudge often sent Pound her candid opinions of members of his new circle, noting of one attentive young researcher who wanted access to Pound's letters (stored at Sant'Ambrogio) that "he seems to have forgotten a lot of his Henry James." There are also discussions of Pound's plans for Rudge, which included her resuming her concert career and translating the rest of Enrico Pea.
Pound's letters during the 1950s became increasingly impersonal, but Rudge's plans for a second visit to St. Elizabeth's sparked a series of letters in which they analyze each other's character, explore their thirty-year relationship, and reflect on past events. These letters begin in late 1954 and continue until Rudge's visit to America in the summer of 1955.